(upbeat music)
- Hello English learners,
welcome back to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
- And I'm Erica.
- And today we are gonna
be talking about the weather.
- That's right, and you know Marco,
this is a really, really useful and
important topic in English, isn't it?
- Exactly because if
you ever travel abroad,
you always wanna know
about the weather, right?
- That's right, and Anglo
people, English people,
all they ever do is
talk about the weather.
- Well, it's an important
topic, you wanna know what
clothes to wear or if you
should take an umbrella.
- Or even when you're
making small talk with people.
- Exactly, so we are gonna be taking a
look at the weather in the United States.
But before we get started with the dialogue,
let's take a look at vocabulary preview.
- Very vocabulary preview.
- Okay, so we have two words
we're gonna hear in the dialogue.
Now the first one is forecast.
- Forecast.
- Weather forecast.
So this is what we listen to or what we see
on the television, the weather forecast.
- Right, it's like the
prediction of the weather.
- Okay, so forecast, can I
only use it in the weather?
- No, of course you can
use it in many other different
situations, like in business,
for example, forecast sales.
- Okay, so the prediction of sales.
Very good, and we have one more
word on vocabulary preview, a shower.
- A shower.
- Shower.
So when it rains for a short time,
and it's not too heavy, that's a shower.
- Okay, very good.
So it's very similar to a shower at home.
- Right, it doesn't
look a little bit of water.
- And it doesn't last too long.
- Okay, very good.
So why don't we listen to our dialogue now?
We are gonna be listening to the weatherman
as he describes the weather in Utah.
(upbeat music)
- And now, let's go to Kenny
Williams for today's weather forecast.
Thank you, Bill, and good
morning, Salt Lake City.
What's the weather we're
looking like today, Kenny?
- Well, it's a bit of a
mixed bag in Utah today.
We've got heavy cloud
cover here, Northern Utah,
and we're calling for scattered
showers throughout the day.
With a daytime high of 45 degrees.
Now, if we move down
to the south of the state,
we can see that a
cold front is moving in.
We can expect clear skies,
but it will be quite cold
with temperatures hovering
around a 30-degree mark.
- So chilly day, folks, so
don't forget your coats.
What about tomorrow, Kenny?
Do you have good news for us?
- Well, it'll be a rainy
day for Northern Utah.
We can expect some isolated
downpours in the morning.
Winds will be coming in from the northeast
with gust reaching 23 miles per hour.
Salt Lake City can expect the
rain to turn to sleep in the evening.
Things are looking a
bit better for the south.
We'll see cloudy skies
with a chance of showers.
Later in the day, we
can expect partly cloudy
skies with a forecast
high of 38 degrees.
- You heard it, folks,
it's gonna be a cold one.
- That's right, Bill.
We'll have more later on
today on the six o'clock news.
That's the weather
forecast for this morning.
(upbeat music)
- All right, so we listen
to the weather forecast
and it doesn't seem like
nice weather in Utah, huh?
- No, it certainly doesn't.
I don't think that I'd
really like to live there.
- Well, maybe it's winter
or something like that.
- Well, I guess maybe it's good for skiing.
- Okay, so now I think it's time for us
to take a look at some of
those maybe difficult words
that we may have listened to in
this dialogue in language takeaway.
- Language takeaway.
All right, here we're gonna
look at some words and
phrases that you can use
to describe the weather.
Now, the first one, we
heard in the weather forecast
that they were calling
for scattered showers.
- Scattered showers.
- Scattered.
- Scattered, if something is scattered.
- It's sort of like, it's a little
bit of that thing everywhere.
- Okay, so, and we already
talked about what showers were.
- Right, so showers a small
bit of a small amount of rain.
- Okay, very good.
To better understand when something is
scattered, imagine that we are in a playground
and the children are
playing in the playground.
- Okay.
- So the children are scattered everywhere.
Some of them are playing on the swing,
some of them are playing
on the grass or in the sandbox.
So children, a little bit of
children in every different spot.
- So if we think that the city is a
playground, maybe in one part of the city,
there's a little bit of rain,
but not in the other part.
- Exactly.
- That's a scattered shower.
- Very good.
Moving on to our second
word, we have hovering.
- Hovering.
- Tempering around the 30 degree mark.
- The temperature is hovering around.
- Okay, so when I say that temperatures
are hovering, you mean it's approximately.
- Okay, so they can move up and down.
So maybe it'll be a little bit warmer
than 30 degrees or a little bit colder.
- Yes.
So if you think of hovering as floating.
- Okay, very good.
So why don't we listen
to some more examples
of how we could use
hovering in different situations?
- Example one.
Unemployment rates are
hovering around the 10% mark
despite the government's
attempts to stimulate the economy.
- Example two.
The way just kept hovering around
us all night was really annoying.
Example three.
The company's margin this year
is hovering around the 40% mark.
- Okay, so pretty clear.
Hovering is sort of
floating around one area.
- Very good.
Now let's move on to the next part.
We saw that we're gonna
have isolated downpours.
- Isolated downpours.
- Okay, let's break this one down.
Let's start with downpours.
- A downpour is when you
have a lot of rain, very strong rain.
- That's right, for maybe a short amount
of time, it's really raining heavily.
- Right, so that's what a downpour is.
And if we take a look
at the first word, isolated.
- So in one small area.
- Okay, confined it to a specific area.
- That's right.
- Okay, so we have an isolated downpour.
It'll be raining in one specific area.
- And you hear this a
lot with weather language.
You hear isolated showers,
isolated snow storms.
- Exactly, so it'll be
in a specific area only.
- All right, so along
with these showers and
rain, we also talked
about wind and we heard
that we will have gusts
reaching 23 miles per hour.
- So we're gonna have gusts
- Gusts of wind.
- Okay, so can you explain
to our listeners what gusts are?
- Okay, so a gust is a sudden
increase in the amount of wind.
- Okay, so maybe we'll have normal wind and
all of a sudden it will get really windy.
- That's right, for a short amount of time.
- Okay, that's a gust.
- G-U-S-T gust.
- Gust of wind.
And for our final word on language
takeaway today, we're gonna have sleep.
- Sleep.
- Oh, sleep.
All right, sleep is a
terrible kind of weather.
It's sort of a mixture
between snow and rain.
- So sleep is kind of the strange
mix between ice and rain and snow.
So just imagine it's not
completely ice, so it's not solid.
But it's not water, right?
It's not rain.
- And that's no either.
- No, it's in the middle.
- Okay.
- All right, so sleep.
But what you really need
to know is that it's terrible.
All right, so that's all the words we
have today for language takeaway.
Let's move on now to fluency builder.
- Fluency builder.
All right, in fluency builder today,
we're gonna look at three phrases
that are really common when
you're talking about the weather.
Now, we heard in the dialogue
that there was a cold front moving in.
- A cold front moving in.
- A cold front is moving in.
- Okay, so a cold front.
- Imagine a wall, a cold air.
And it comes towards a place and then it
changes the pressure in the atmosphere.
- Okay, so a very sudden amount
of cold air that comes into a place.
- Right.
- So we say a cold front is moving in.
- Mm-hmm, so we always think of
these cold fronts or warm fronts as moving.
So you can either say they're moving in
or you can say a cold front is coming in.
- Okay, very good.
And okay, we have a cold
front that's moving in and we're
gonna have winds that will be
coming in from the northeast.
- Okay, winds coming in from.
So when I say it's coming in from, you're
talking about its origin where it starts.
- Okay, so if I change the
noun and I say, and I don't
say winds anymore, but
maybe I'll say my friends.
My friends are coming
in from Chicago, Chicago.
So they are arriving from Chicago.
- Exactly.
- What else can I say?
- Or you can also say the kids
are coming in from outside.
- Okay, so where they
were before, very good.
So coming in from, you
can change the noun a
little bit and you can
form these new sentences.
- Great, now our final phrase, we heard the
announcer say, "It's gonna be a cold one.
" - It's gonna be a cold one.
- It's gonna be a cold one.
- So I have this phrase,
it's gonna be a cold one.
What do I mean by a cold one?
- Okay, so the one represents the event.
So the day, so it's gonna be a cold day.
- Yes.
- Okay.
- Now we can obviously
change the adjective, right?
So it's gonna be a hot one,
it's gonna be a long one.
It's gonna be a long day.
- All right.
- But the one can mean anything.
- Okay, so it can be a day,
it can be an event meeting.
- Okay.
- A project.
So for example, if we're
going to a meeting,
I might say, hey Marco,
this is gonna be a hard one.
- Okay, so the one represents the meeting.
- That's right.
- This is gonna be a hard meeting.
All right, I think this is a very good
phrase and it's very commonly used.
So why don't we listen
to some more examples
of how we can use, it's
gonna be a something one.
- Example one.
- Temperatures of forecasted
to hit 37 degrees today.
It's going to be a hot one folks.
- Example two.
- It's only eight a.m.
And I've got a hundred emails already.
It's gonna be a long one today.
- Example three.
I haven't studied at all for the exam.
It's gonna be a tough one.
- Okay, so some great examples
and I think it's time for us
to listen to this dialogue again
and now we can understand all these words
and phrases that we've just talked about.
- And now, let's go to Kenny
Williams for today's weather forecast.
- Thank you Bill and good
morning, Salt Lake City.
What's the weather we're
looking like today, Kenny?
- Well, it's a bit of a
mixed bag in Utah today.
We've got heavy cloud
cover here in northern Utah
and we're calling for scattered
showers throughout the day.
With a daytime high of 45 degrees.
Now, if we move down
to the south of the state,
we can see that a
cold front is moving in.
We can expect clear skies
but it will be quite cold
with temperatures hovering
around the 30 degree mark.
- It's a chilly day, folks.
So don't forget your coats.
What about tomorrow, Kenny?
Do you have good news for us?
- Well, it'll be a rainy
day for northern Utah.
We can expect some isolated
downpours in the morning.
Winds will be coming in from the northeast
with gust reaching 23 miles per hour.
Salt Lake City can expect the
rain to turn to sleep in the evening.
Things are looking a
bit better for the south.
We'll see cloudy skies
with a chance of showers.
Later in the day, we
can expect partly cloudy
skies with a forecast
high of 38 degrees.
- You heard it, folks,
it's gonna be a cold one.
- That's right, Bill.
We'll have more later on
today on the six o'clock news.
That's the weather
forecast for this morning.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, so we know that in
English speaking countries,
the weather is always
always always a great subject
of conversation for a small talk, right?
- Exactly.
If you ever wanna talk
to somebody or start a
conversation, the weather
is always a number one topic.
- Yep, and we actually have
a phrase in this dialogue.
There'll be great for
starting a conversation.
Like for example, imagine
if you lived here in Utah
and you were wanting to start
a conversation with someone,
you could say, "It sure is
a cold one today, isn't it?
" - Exactly.
That's a great way of starting
a conversation and English
speaking people love to talk
about the weather, as you say.
- That's right, so guys, if
you have any questions
about weather vocabulary,
or if you wanna practice
talking about the weather,
come to our website englishpod.
com.
- Right, Erica and I are always there to
answer any questions or doubts you may have.
And also, if you have any
stories about crazy weather,
maybe in the countries
you're from, let us know.
- So, thanks for downloading
you guys and until next time, bye.
(upbeat music)